<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC
  "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
  "http://www.discursive.com/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chapter-plugin-management">
  <title>Managing Hudson Plugins</title>

  <para>Hudson plugin management is available via
    <option>Manage Hudson</option>
    and selecting the
    <option>Manage Plugins</option>
    link shown in<xref linkend="fig-config-manage-hudson"/>. This
    administration interface allows you see what plugin versions are
    currently installed, update them and install new ones as well as manage
    some advanced settings to work with the multitude of plugins available
    for Hudson. Using plugins allows you to support many new features beyond
    a basic Hudson install as well as tweak the user interface and morph
    Hudson into the CI server you need.
  </para>

  <section id="section-plugin-management-installed">
    <title>Installed</title>
    <para>To get a list of installed plugins, click in the
      <option>Installed</option>
      tab. This will display a list all of the Hudson plugins currently
      installed on your instance of Hudson system.
    </para>

    <figure id="fig-using-installed-plugin">
      <title>The Installed tab for managing the installed plugins</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="web">
          <imagedata contentdepth="100%"
                     fileref="figs/web/plugin-mgt-installed.png" scalefit="1"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="print">
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="figs/print/plugin-mgt-installed.pdf" scalefit="0"
                     width="100%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>The
      <option>Enabled</option>
      check box allows you to activate and deactivate specific plugins. After
      plugin updates your old plugin version will remain to be accessible and
      you can downgrade to the older version by pressing the
      <option>Downgrade to x.y.z</option>
      button. The pinned column will then be marked for this plugin so that
      automatic update will not occur until you unpinned the version. Any
      changes will require you to restart Hudson by clicking the
      <option>Restart once no jobs are running</option>
      button as displayed in <xref linkend="fig-plugin-mgt-progress"/> to take
      affect.
    </para>
    <figure id="fig-plugin-mgt-progress">
      <title>Install and update plugin progress screen ready to restart the
        server</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="web">
          <imagedata contentdepth="100%"
                     fileref="figs/web/plugin-mgt-progress.png" scalefit="1"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="print">
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="figs/print/plugin-mgt-progress.pdf" scalefit="0"
                     width="100%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

  </section>

  <section id="section-plugin-management-available">
    <title>Available</title>
    <para>This list of available plugins includes hundreds of useful utilities,
      tweaks and feature sets which extend the core feature set of Hudson. The
      list is separated into topics and contains a short description for each
      plugin as well as a link to the plugin web site. In order to install a
      plugin simply select the check box in the plugin row, press the
      <option>Install</option>
      button on the bottom of the list. This will redirect to a progress
      reporting page. After a success message you will have to restart
      Hudson by clicking the
      <option>Restart once no jobs are running</option>
      button for the new plugin to be available.
    </para>

    <figure id="fig-using-avail-plugin">
      <title>The Available tab for installing new plugins</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="web">
          <imagedata contentdepth="100%"
                     fileref="figs/web/plugin-mgt-available.png" scalefit="1"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="print">
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="figs/print/plugin-mgt-available.pdf" scalefit="0"
                     width="100%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section id="section-plugin-management-updates">
    <title>Updates</title>

    <para>Hudson regularly checks an available list of Hudson plugins on the
      Hudson web site and will notify if an updates become available. To see if
      any updates are currently available click on the
      <option>Updates</option>
      tab in the Manage Plugins screen. Plugin eligible for an update will be
      displayed next to the available update version and the version which is
      currently installed. To update a plugin select the check box in the
      <option>Install</option>
      column and press the
      <option>Install</option>
      button on the bottom of the list. This will redirect to a progress
      reporting page. After a success message you will have to restart Hudson by
      clicking the
      <option>Restart once no jobs are running</option>
      button for the new plugin to be available.
    </para>

    <figure id="fig-using-updates-plugin">
      <title>The Updates tab displaying available updates of installed plugins</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="web">
          <imagedata contentdepth="100%"
                     fileref="figs/web/plugin-mgt-updates.png" scalefit="1"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="print">
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="figs/print/plugin-mgt-updates.pdf"
                     scalefit="0" width="100%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section id="section-plugin-management-advanced">
    <title>Advanced</title>
    <para>The Advanced tab as displayed in
      <xref linkend="fig-plugin-mgt-advanced"/> allows you to
      configure the proxy
      settings for
      Hudson to be able to connect to the plugin repository on the Hudson web
      site, upload Hudson plugin files (<code>*.hpi</code>) manually to
      install e.g. custom plugins and specify the url for a custom update
      site.
      <figure id="fig-plugin-mgt-advanced">
        <title>The Advanced tab for miscellaneous plugin management tasks</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata contentdepth="100%"
                       fileref="figs/web/plugin-mgt-advanced.png" scalefit="1"/>
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="figs/print/plugin-mgt-advanced.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </para>

    <section>
      <title>HTTP Proxy Configuration</title>
      <para>Hudson retrieves a list of plugins and downloads plugins over the
        public internet. If your server is behind a proxy server, you will need
        to configure the proxy settings. Supply the necessary values to connect
        to your internal proxy in the <option>Server</option> and
        <option>Port</option> fields. The
        <option>No Proxy for</option>
        field allows you to exclude host names from proxying by adding them in a
        comma separated list.If your proxy server requires authentication you
        will have to select the
        <option>Proxy Needs Authorization</option>
        check box and provide the
        <option>User name</option>
        and<option>Password</option>.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Upload Plugin</title>
      <para>Hudson plugins are distributed as <code>.hpi</code> files and the
        the Advanced administration section allows you to upload them with a
        file chooser. This feature is especially useful for installing
        custom, in house developed plugins or commercially distributed
        plugins that are not available on the update site. You can also use
        it to install plugins you build from source during development or
        when helping by contributing fixes to open source plugins.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Update Site</title>
      <para>Instead of using the public update site on the Hudson web site
        you can host your own plugin repository and you could then add the
        <option>URL</option> in the available input field.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
